My father was a brilliant man. He was leader of the people who were fighting the British.
मेरे पिता एक मेधावी व्यक्ति थे। वह उन लोगों के नेता थे जो अंग्रेजों से लड़ रहे थे।
Very learned, very learned man. He went to jail many a times. Last time, when he
बहुत विद्वान, अत्यंत विद्वान व्यक्ति। वह कई बार जेल गए। पिछली बार जब वह
went after 1942 movement, it was for three years regularly he was in jail.
1942 के आंदोलन के बाद गए, तीन साल नियमित रूप से वे जेल में रहे।
But there was one fellow who was a friend of My father, he came and told My mother
लेकिन मेरे पिता के एक साथी थे जो उनके दोस्त भी थे, उन्होंने मेरी माता के पास आकर कहा
that you must apologize because we don't want your husband to be in jail, he has so
कि, "आपको माफी मांगनी चाहिए क्योंकि हम नहीं चाहते हैं कि आपके पति जेल में रहें, उनके पास
many children and this and that. My mother said, "I can't do that. His will. He wants
कई बच्चे हैं और यह और वह।" मेरी मां ने कहा, "मैं ऐसा नहीं कर सकती। उनकी इच्छा। वह
to go to jail, he has to go." Like that, you see, we have glimpses of very ideal
जेल जाना चाहते हैं, उन्हें जाना होगा।" ऐसे ही, आप देखिए, हमारे पास बहुत आदर्श की झलकियां हैं
type of people during that time. They didn't think of money, their properties, nothing.
उस समय के इस प्रकार के लोगों की। वे पैसे के बारे में नहीं सोचते, अपनी संपत्ति, कुछ भी नहीं।
So, sacrifice was immense. Nowadays we can't even think of such a thing.
तो, बलिदान अपार था। आजकल हम ऐसी बात सोच भी नहीं सकते।
But I did feel that the English should leave our country. They have no right to be there.
लेकिन मुझे भी लगा कि अंग्रेजों को हमारा देश छोड़ देना चाहिए। उन्हें वहां रहने का कोई अधिकार नहीं है।
So, I did feel that somebody has to tell them that this is wrong. So, I had a great
तो, मैंने महसूस किया कि किसी को उन्हें बताना होगा कि यह गलत है। तो, मेरे पास
sense of right and wrong but I didn't know it was Spirituality. It was a innate
सही और गलत की एक महान समझदारी थी लेकिन मैं नहीं जानती थी कि यह अध्यात्म है। यह एक जन्मजात
quality (with)in Me. But most of the people, in those days were like that, in India
गुण था मुझमें। लेकिन उन दिनों भारत में अधिकांश लोग, ऐसे ही थे
because the urge for freedom was so great and that people were fighting for freedom,
क्योंकि आजादी की ललक इतनी महान थी और लोग आजादी के लिए लड़ रहे थे,
so they could not think of all those things. Once I had to speak when I was
इसलिए वे उन सब चीज़ों के बारे में नहीं सोच सकते थे। एक बार जब मेरी
7 years of age, for Mahatma Gandhi's fasting and I spoke to thousands of people
उम्र 7 साल की थी, तब मुझे बोलना था महात्मा गांधी के उपवास पर और मैंने हज़ारों लोगों से बात की।
I was a little girl and I told them how we should forget about caste system and how
मैं एक छोटी लड़की थी और मैंने उन्हें बताया कि हमें कैसे जाति व्यवस्था के बारे में भूल जाना चाहिए और कैसे
we should marry each other. I was such a little girl as 7 years.
हमें आपस में शादी कर लेनी चाहिए। मैं 7 साल की इतनी छोटी लड़की थी।